<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - angr]]></title><description><![CDATA[writings from zac anger]]></description><link>http://blog.zacanger.com/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 16:13:37 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zacanger.com/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Forty Reasons To Wonder Why The Fuck You Love Apple]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>A response to <a href="http://www.networkworld.com/article/3050934/macs/on-its-40th-anniversary-40-things-we-love-about-apple.html">this
absurdity</a>.</p>
<p>These are literally just a summary of each of those slides.</p>
<ul>
<li>Apple has a marketing team</li>
<li>their users are obsessed</li>
<li>they make decent clones of other products years after those products are the norm</li>
<li>they don&#39;t know their own target demographic</li>
<li>they make products</li>
<li>they make the same products year after year and announce them as if they&#39;re new</li>
<li>they make inferior products and market them as if they&#39;re worth buying</li>
<li>they still don&#39;t know their own users</li>
<li>their users are still obsessed</li>
<li>they have stores that sell their products</li>
<li>they put their products in boxes</li>
<li>they offer short-term care for their products after you buy them</li>
<li>they have stores that you have to wait to get into</li>
<li>they make products</li>
<li>they made products years ago, too</li>
<li>their products were not the exact same products as other products, years ago</li>
<li>one of the products they used to make was a printer</li>
<li>they also used to make... products</li>
<li>like an idiot, i don&#39;t back up my data. and when a hard drive fails, i prefer to buy a new computer of a different
brand and then blame an entire major segment of consumer electronics for my own stupidity.</li>
<li>i noce bought one of their products</li>
<li>they make overpriced things that don&#39;t offer anything that any other platform doesn&#39;t have, but i by their crap anyway</li>
<li>their smartphones offer all the same functionality that flip phones have</li>
<li>they make apps</li>
<li>at one point the company almost totally failed, but then didn&#39;t</li>
<li>some people who work at Apple aren&#39;t native English speakers</li>
<li>i buy their products both for myself and for my kids sometimes</li>
<li>they made another &#39;new&#39; product that had already been on the market for years</li>
<li>they even had a marketing team back when CDs were still a thing</li>
<li>they made a really shitty mouse that everyone hated, aww, look at them trying, so cute</li>
<li>applescript is such a joke that it wasn&#39;t going to be included in OS X until, whoops, someone put them on the spot
about it</li>
<li>there is a voice assistant</li>
<li>Apple had a version of BASIC which was almost the same but not <em>exactly</em> the same as any of the other BASICs on the
market at the time</li>
<li>they had PR person that nobody liked</li>
<li>their computers can run software, including some games</li>
<li>they have stores not just where you are but in other places also</li>
<li>they have both marketing and PR people</li>
<li>they sometimes sponsor events, in the same way that most large companies sometimes sponsor events</li>
<li>they sometimes have TV commercials</li>
<li>there are people who like their products enough to sometimes write about them</li>
</ul>
<p>... are you fucking kidding me?</p>
<p>Here&#39;s a couple of things to like about Macs/Apple. Keep in mind that I don&#39;t own any Apple products, and haven&#39;t owned
any since before Mac OS X. I have used them regularly over the past several years, though.</p>
<ul>
<li>Their hardware doesn&#39;t suck. It&#39;s not great, performance-wise, for the price, but it&#39;s good hardware.<ul>
<li>Great battery life (due to the fancy it&#39;s-not-in-just-one-place-in-your-laptop battery).</li>
<li>Great displays (if you pay for the great display).</li>
<li>The cases (speaking of their laptops, here) are <em>gorgeous</em>.</li>
<li>They&#39;re super light. Yes, there are Windows laptops that are also super light. Those Windows laptops also probably
cost less and are more powerful, generally. But you can get a powerful Mac that&#39;s also lightweight (for like $3500).</li>
<li>The keyboards, while annoyingly different from literally every other type of computer ever, have a nice feel.
(My current laptop, and the one I used just prior to this one, had equally good keyboards. They&#39;re not only a
Mac thing.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Under the hood, Mac OS X is a (gimped) BSD. It&#39;s a PITA sometimes to actually get to the good parts, and it&#39;s a lot
easier to just throw Linux on a (much cheaper, probably faster) laptop, but it can be made into a really nice
development environment. It takes some work on any platform (and is virtually impossible on Windows, unless you&#39;re
developing to target Windows), but on Macs it&#39;s a little more difficult to get to the UNIX-y bits than on a Linux or
BSD.</li>
<li>Macs are trendy. People who really believe they &#39;think different&#39; will think you&#39;re cool for having one. Of course,
all that means is that you believe the same marketing as those people, but they&#39;re not a bad bunch to be kinda lumped
together with, usually.</li>
<li>There&#39;s some software (and I&#39;m thinking specifically of design software here) that just isn&#39;t available for other
platforms. I still can&#39;t accept that it&#39;s a good idea to only target Mac, but The Omni Group has been doing it for
like 27 years and they&#39;re still around, so I guess it works. This fits in with the whole &#39;we make products for a
specific type of person and if you are that type of person you NEED to use this product&#39; kind of marketing though.
There are great design tools available on Windows (Adobe products, for example, or Macaw). There are even great tools
for Linux. Go ahead and laugh at GIMP and Inkscape -- they&#39;ve been around forever and are <em>incredibly</em> powerful. And
we (Linux users) also have Scribus, Blender, Lightworks, Krita, Radiance, Darktable (which is hands-down the best RAW
editor I&#39;ve ever seen), and a host of fantastic video tools -- plus, of course, ImageMagick and everything that
allows.</li>
<li>Mac OS X isn&#39;t Windows.<ul>
<li>I should say that Windows <em>is</em> good at some things. I think. Not the OS itself, but having the OS, it&#39;s probably a
good idea if you&#39;re really into games, or developing specifically for Microsoft products (VB, C#, whatever).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
]]></description><link>/2016/forty-reasons-to-wonder-why-the-fuck-you-love-apple.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/forty-reasons-to-wonder-why-the-fuck-you-love-apple.html</guid><category><![CDATA[apple]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[zac anger]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2016 18:14:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>