<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[undefined - angr]]></title><description><![CDATA[writings from zac anger]]></description><link>http://blog.zacanger.com/</link><generator>Ghost</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 03:19:00 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zacanger.com/tag/undefined/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[a short rant about languages and people]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I wrote this on <a href="https://mastodon.social/@zacanger">Mastodon</a> but decided
to cross-post for whatever reason.</p>
<p>One of my biggest pet peeves is when people talk about how great foo-lang is as
an alernative to bar-lang, &amp; it turns out they&#39;re just shit at bar-lang, or
write deliberately bad bar-lang in examples to try to make foo-lang look better.
Don&#39;t do that. If you can&#39;t write decent, idiomatic bar-lang, you don&#39;t get to
hate it yet. If you <em>can</em> and are writing it like someone who&#39;s never read a
tutorial on it intentionally, you&#39;re just making foo-lang&#39;s community look like
assholes.  Chances are foo-lang is pretty great, &amp; can stand up on its own
merits. Talk about those, not how bad your half-assed bar-lang is in comparison.
I see this a lot with functional languages that compile to JS, especially, &amp;
it&#39;s sad, because most of those languages are actually really neat &amp; there are a
lot of good reasons to try them, but people saying &#39;look how horrible this JS is
compared to this other thing&#39; when the JS looks like it was written by someone
who skimmed a jQuery tutorial once <em>really</em> doesn&#39;t present the community very
well. So don&#39;t do that.</p>
<p>Also: a fun vim/Twitter trick (I also cross-posted this to
<a href="https://twitter.com/zacanger">Twitter</a> ): <code>:set textwidth=140</code>, then <code>gq</code>.
You&#39;re welcome.</p>
]]></description><link>/2017/short-rant-on-languages.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">/2017/short-rant-on-languages.html</guid><category><![CDATA[lang]]></category><category><![CDATA[community]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[zac anger]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 03:13:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>